Guide to the Ethnic Fraternal Organizations Oral History Project Collection, 1975-1976 AIS.1976.25
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Ethnic Fraternal Organizations Oral History Project Collection
1975-1976
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh. Department of History
AIS.1976.25
2.5 Linear Feet (plus 445 audiocassette tapes)
The Ethnic Fraternal Organizations Oral History Project consists of taperecorded oral interviews from a project conducted by the University of Pittsburgh Department of History which explores the roles and influences of ethnic fraternal organizations in the Jewish, Black, Croatian, Italian, Polish and other ethnic communities in the Pittsburgh area; partly transcribed; limited indexing.
History
In June 1975, through a grant from the Buhl Foundation, the Oral History Program for Western Pennsylvania was established at the University of Pittsburgh. Using interviewers from the University and the community, the program sought to explore the roles and influences of ethnic fraternal organizations in the principally Jewish Black, Croatian, Italian, and Polish communities in the Pittsburgh area. There are a few interviews with individuals of Austrian, French Lithuanian, Greek, Irish, Rumanian, Slovak, and Spanish descent.
Acquisition Information
On deposit from the Department of History, University of Pittsburgh, August 1976.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Previous Citation
Ethnic Fraternal Organizations Oral History Project Collection, 1975-1976, AIS.1976.25, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Scope and Content Notes
The Ethnic Fraternal Organizations Oral History Project consists of taperecorded oral interviews from a project conducted by the University of Pittsburgh Department of History which explores the roles and influences of ethnic fraternal organizations in the Jewish, Black, Croatian, Italian, Polish and other ethnic communities in the Pittsburgh area; partly transcribed; limited indexing.
Contains: project data; case files; interview cassettes; photographs; Pennsylvania Oral History Conference tapes; and non project files including Italo American interview tapes and commentary sheets; and three transcriptions from the Bradford community interviews.
Project administrators were Stephen P. Zupcic and Margie Gillcrese.
Availability of electronic audio recordings
All cassette tapes have been transferred to digital audio files are are available online:
https://historicpittsburgh.org/collection/ethnic-fraternal-organizations-oral-history-project-collection
https://digital.library.pitt.edu/collection/ethnic-fraternal-organizations-oral-history-project-collection
African Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Societies and clubs; Italian American fraternal organizations -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Polish American fraternal organizations -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Fraternal organizations -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Transcripts; Oral histories (Document genres); Interviews; Italian Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Societies and clubs; Italian Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Bradford -- Societies and clubs; Audiocassettes; Photographs; Associations, institutions, etc. -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Ethnicity -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Societies and clubs; Polish Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Societies, etc.; Croatian Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Societies and clubs; Ethnic groups; Jews -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Societies and clubs; Ethnic Fraternal Organizations Oral History Project (University of Pittsburgh)
- Project Data, 1975-1976; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Includes questionnaires and a brief descriptive narrative of the project.
  - Project Data (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Project Files, 1975-1976; II.
  Individual files contain case files and taped interviews. Although not all case files are complete, a case file is in three parts: the interview cover sheet, indexing and interview transcription. All case files contain the interview cover sheet. This contains information on: ethnicity; respondent's name; address; telephone number; interviewer's name; his address and telephone; date of interview; place of interview; tape length; fraternal membership; outstanding features about interview; comments of the interviewer.
  If the case file contains indexing or an interview transcription, it is indicated below with an "x". The index is more accurately described as a table of contents. An "x" in front of the name means a duplicate tape has been made.
  - Interviewees, 1.
    Although not all case files are complete, a case file is in three parts: the interview cover sheet, indexing and interview transcription. All case files contain the interview cover sheet. This contains information on: ethnicity; respondent's name; address; telephone number; interviewer's name; his address and telephone; date of interview; place of interview; tape length; fraternal membership; outstanding features about interview; and comments of the interviewer.
    A master inventory exists in the collection case file which indciates if an interview transcription exists, if the interview was indexed, the length of the interview, number of tape cassettes and if a photograph(s) exists of the respondent. Please check with Archives Service Center staff for more information.
    There are no file folders containing cover sheets, indexing, etc. for the following names: Kuswa, Mrs. (Slovak) and Lanier, Elizabeth L. (Italian). However, tapes of the two interviews can be found in the cassette cabinet.
    - Ambromovich, John (Croatian) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Aika, Thomas (Black) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Alberts, Ann (Jewish) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Alexander, Joyce (Black) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Allen, Dorothy (Black) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Allesberry, Ellen (Black) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Alonzo, Jose (Spanish) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Antoncic, Magdalene (Croatian) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Arnold, Minnie(Black) (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Baccelli, Angela S. (Italian) (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Baer, Stanley (Jewish) (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Bailey, Henry R. (Black) (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Bartolomucci, A. R. (Italian) (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Baruch, Herbert A. (Jewish) (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Baum, Ludwig (Jewish) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Baum, Margaritta (Jewish) (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Beamer, Delmas (Black) (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Beckum, Mrs. OtLabrice (Black) (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Bedic, Amelia (Croatian) (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Benedict, Mrs. Rea (Jewish) (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Berman, Helen(Jewish) (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Biggs, Lillian (Black) (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Birnkrant, Saul (Jewish) (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Bogess, Charles S. (Black) (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Borgna, Mrs. Lucia T. (Italian) (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Bosiljevac, Anna (Croatian), Tape missing as of June 19, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Brock, William X. (Black) (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Brown, Clare (Black) (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Buchwald, Anna (Jewish) (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Buchwald, Frank (Jewish) (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Burke, Ethel (Jewish) (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Caddle, Elizabeth (Black) (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Cafardi, Alexander (Italian) (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Cafardi, Jennie J. (Italian) (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Caplan, Henry (Jewish) (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Capozoli, Pasquale (Italian) (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Carey, Frances (Jewish) (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Carr, Mary (Croatian) (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Carr, Walter E. (Irish) (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Cascaito, Emma (Italian) (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Churilla, Stephen (Slovak) (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Cohen, Lena (Jewish) (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Colpo, Alfonso (Italian) (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Contis, Tom (Greek) (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Cooper, Charlotte (Russian-Jew) (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Cooper, Peter R. (Russian-Jew) (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Davis, John (Black) (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Davis, Dr. LaFayette (Black) (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - De Lostratto, J. & M. (Italian) (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Del Bianco, Albert (Italian) (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Del Bianco, Trancuillo (Italian) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Devurich, Stephen (Croatian) (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Di Cecco, Susan (Italian) (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Di Ricco, Peter L. (Italian) (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Dickson, Corrine (Black) (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Diggs, Samuel L. (Black) (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Dorsey, Mrs. Zuber (Black) (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Dudzinski, Stanley J. (Polish) (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Dujmic, Barbara (Croatian) (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Dujmic, Matthew (Croatian) (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Duralia, Daul (Croatian) (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Elovitz, Celia (Jewish) (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Esther, Mrs. Henrye (Black) (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Ferrainolo, Joseph (Italian) (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Finch, Lester (Black) (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Franchini, Romeo (Italian) (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Frederick, George (Croatian) (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Frediuni, Mrs. Pi (Italian) (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Freedman, Leah (Jewish) (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Freeman, Hyman (Russian-Jew) (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Freeman, Lillian (Russian-Jew) (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Freuthal, Paul (Jewish) (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Gallo, Frank S. (Italian) (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Gardner, Catherine (Black) (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Gasparich, Mary (Croatian) (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Gedunsky, Anna (Jewish) (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Gelb, Morris (Jewish) (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Giampolo, Carl, Sr. (Italian) (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Gibbs, Viola (Black) (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Givens, Joseph (Black) (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Glick, Lea (Jewish) (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Golomb, Bernard (Jewish) (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Graham, Mrs. Bern (Black) (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Grasha, Michael (Croatian) (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Green, Mrs. Laura Lee (Black) (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Green, Mrs. Paulene (Black) (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Hairston, Bessie R. (Black) (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Harring, Anna Mae (Black) (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Hersh, Dr. Joseph (Jewish) (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Hicks, Lucille (Black) (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Hischuck, George (Austrian) (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Hitchcock, Lillian (Black) (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Hoechstetter, Frances (Jewish) (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Hoffman, Hyman (Jewish) (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Howard Moore, Fannie D. (Black) (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Hunt, Helen (Black) (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Iaquinta, Micheline (Italian) (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - James, Thelma (Black) (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Janeski, Antoinette (Polish) (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Johnson, Marshall S. (Black) (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Johnson, Rosalee (Black) (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Jones, Lillian (Black) (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Jones, Matthew (Black) (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Kaplan, Naomi(Jewish) (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Katonik, John (Croatian) (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Keys, Emma (Black) (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Kincaid, Laiary (German-Irish) (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Kladusan, Anthony (Croatian) (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Kondrit, Anna (Polish-Ukrainian) (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Korn, Reuben (Jewish) (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Krajncich, Mrs. Zlata (Croatian) (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Krotec, Sophia(Croatian) (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Kwalwasser, Jacob (Jewish) (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Laban, George E. (Black) (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Laboon, John F. (French-Lithuanian) (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Lamberti, Joseph (Italian) (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Landes, Rabbi Morris (Jewish) (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Lanzetta, Frank (Italian) (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Laurella, Mr. Carmen (Italian) (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Lavine, Rose (Jewish) (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Lebovitz, Bernard (Jewish) (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Lebowitz, Harry (Jewish) (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Lech, Joseph (Polish) (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Lee, Elizabeth (Black) (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Levenson, Yetta (Jewish) (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Levin, Celia (Jewish) (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Lindsay, Willie May (Black) (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Lippman, Walter (Jewish) (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Lloyd, Eva (Black) (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Lucas, Ralston (Black) (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Lagram, Sam (Jewish) (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Majetich, Antonia (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Markus, Alfred(Jewish) (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - McKula, Stephen (Austrian) (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - McNairy, Gladys B. (Black) (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Melani, Louis (Italian) (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Melman, Morris (Jewish) (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Miller, Helen (Black) (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Miller, Joseph J. (German) (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Mintz, Ida (Jewish) (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Mitchell, Mattie (Black) (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Monroe, James B. (Black) (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Moore, Howard L. (Black) (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Morton, Carrie(Black) (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Moutry, Juanita (Black) (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Munley, Pauline (Italian) (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Murdoch, Ethel (Black) (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Newman, Esther (Jewish) (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Nixon, Anne (Black) (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Norman, Willie C. (Black) (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Orringer, Morris (Jewish) (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Ottenheimer, Fritz (Jewish) (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Pace, Mrs. Frankie W. (Black) (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Pace, Ms. Frankie W. (Black) (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Pacella, Raphael M. (Italian) (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Palilla, Lena (Italian) (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Parrish, Frazier (Black) (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Paterni, Agnes(Italian) (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Pausics Carolyn (Rumanian) (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Pausic, Matt (Rumanian) (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Perkovic, Barbara (Croatian) (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Pervin, Abraham (Jewish) (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Pervin, Stella (Jewish) (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Pettet, Rev. Weldon D. (Black) (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Phister, Ann Bozic (Croatian) (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Pinkus, Ernst (Jewish) (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Pitts, Robert (Black) (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Przybylek, Walter P. (Polish) (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Puskarich, John (Croatian) (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Raphael, Frances (Russian) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Rapoports Harry (Jewish) (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Reinkrant, Dr. Pauline (Jewish) (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Rosenfield, Ernestine Ann (Jewish) (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Rosenthal, Ida(Jewish) (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Rubenstein, Beatrice (Jewish) (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Rubenstein, David (Jewish) (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Rubenstein, Frieda (Jewish) (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Rubinstein, Louis (Jewish) (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Sallie, James C. (Black) (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Sambol, Theresa (Slovenian) (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Sands, Harold (Black) (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Saul, Joseph (Jewish) (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Schatzel, Alcuin (German) (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Scheinberg, Helen (Jewish) (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Schey, Sigmund (Jewish) (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Sestric, Mary (Croatian) (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Shaginaw, Barbara (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Siegman, Joseph (Jewish) (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Silvestri, Silvestri (Italian) (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Simon, Dora (Jewish) (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Slawkin, Harry(Jewish) (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Smith, David Miller (Scottish) (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Smith, Henry (Black) (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Smith, Lawrence R. (Black) (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Smith, Lester (Black) (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Smooke, Zoltan (Jewish) (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Sodini, Joseph (Italian) (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Sorace, Mary (Italian) (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Sparks, Noble B. (Black) (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Spudich, Nicholas (Croatian) (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Stark, Sadie (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Stern, Martin (Jewish) (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Stewart, Rachel (Russian-Jew) (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Sumpter, Louise (Black) (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Taylor, Richard (Black) (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Thomas, Clara E. (Black) (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Thomass, Grace (Black) (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Thomas, Mrs. Nathan (Black) (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Tisdale, Alberta M. (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Topolsky, Bess (Jewish) (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Tridina, Catherine (Croatian) (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Tuckers Ruth L. (Black) (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Tucker, Zebedee (Black) (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Turk, Natnan (Jewish) (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Uvodich, Angelina (Croatian) (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Vranes, Milan (Croatian) (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Vranesh, George (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Washington, Althea (Black) (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Washington, Calvin (Black) (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Wasserman, Lillian (Jewish) (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - Wedner, Flarence (Jewish) (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - Weissman, Radie (Jewish) (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - West, George L. (Black) (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Whites Mary (Black) (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - Wyland, Stephanie (Polish) (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Yohovich, Joseph (Croatian) (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Young, Ars. Jessie (Jewish) (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Zahorsky, Michael (Slovak) (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Zgainer, Gabriel (Croatian) (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Zsainer, Mrs. Louise (Croatian) (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - Zionts, Samuel E. (Jewish) (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - Zupcic, Joseph (Croatian) (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Zupcic, Stephen (Croatian) (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - Zwang, Jacob (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Photographs, 2.
    Photographs exist for 60 individuals but only 26 of them have been identified.
    - Photographs (Box 5)
- Pennsylvania Oral History Conference, Balch Institute, Philadelphia, June 4-5, 1976; III.
- Non Project Files, 1976; IV.
  - Italian American Tape Project, 1976; 1.
    - Tape Commentary Sheets (Box 4)
      Includes project questionnaire and comments of two interviewers, William Goncar and Carmen D. Piccirillo.
    - Tapes
      Includes Piccirillo interviews with Francisco Basilone, Josephine Martucci, and Patricia Martucci (2 tapes); and Goncar interviews with four generations of Italo Americans (1 tape).
  - Bradford Tapes, 1976-1977; 2.
    Includes three transcriptions of interviews with Bradford residents regarding their viewpoints towards the history of the community. Contains interviews with Margaret Bacon, Antimo Bagnoli, Joseph Cici, Marty McIntyre, and Angelo Statti.
  - Miscellaneous Tapes, 1968, 1975-1976; 3.
    Includes four separate interviews on various topics. There are two full and two partial interviews. Contains: partial interview with Bartol Francic concerning the Croation Fraternal Union; full interview with Luigi Gurrere concerning the Italian immigrant experience and Pittsburgh ethnic history; partial interview with Mrs. J. Leonard Levy concerning Jewish-American home life; and full interview with Bernard J. Piatt regaridng his life and the town of his residence, Angelica, N.Y.